I'm sorry to ask, uh, this question
almost, but it's something that I
think is a little bit important.
Um, how do you think it affects the
culture of a community of a project
when the leader is on that projects?
Uh, public mailing.
Telling people in response to
Patrick views that they should
be retroactively aborted.
Right.
And maybe that you're surprised that
they're still alive because they
should have starved to death when
they were children, because they were
too stupid to find a ship to suck on.
I, I agree that some people might feel
put off by that, but on the other hand,
You know what I, in the end, I don't care.
Right.
I care about technology and I've actually
seen projects that took the whole
political correctness so far that the
project no longer is about the tech.
Um, I actually, so my, wow,
we're getting more questions.
I think at some point we
may want to moderate them.
So my team don't get you.
I actually am very happy
to talk about this.
It's not a problem for me.
Um, my standpoint has always been
that, Hey, people are different.
I'm abrasive.
I grew up in a culture that I think is
not quite as politically correct as the
culture, especially in the U S today.
I also grew up in a family
that was largely dysfunctional.
So, um, I mean, so people are
different and some people take
offense and some people give offense
and we all have to live together.
But the living together is not by
finding some lowest common denominator.
The living together.
And it has actually been fairly
successful is to try and realize
that, Hey, unlike your family, you
can actually pick your friends and
you can take the coworkers and open
source is actually really good at that.
Better so than many commercial software
projects, because in commercial setting,
you're kind of stuck with your boss
in open source, find people you like
find people you like working with.
Um, I, I work directly with.
Let's say 20 people closely and
50 people more or less, right?
There's every release.
There's a thousand people involved
find somebody who liked better than me.
That's fine.
Right.
I'm not willing to be less honest.
Uh, because I know I'm abrasive, right.
And quite often the whole, like when I
say something like, I wonder how he grew
to be an adult when he's so stupid that
he, I don't expect him to find food.
Some people might realize that
it's kind of hyperbole and joke.
Not I'm not.
I'm not saying something
bad that, you know, it's not
politically correct or whatever.
Although certainly I would understand if
people do say this, it's more about, um,
treating other people with respect and
maybe technical, you know what I mean?
You going to flow at everything you
want, but I don't respect people on this.
I think they deserve the respect.
There are people who think that respect
is something that should be given.
And I happened to be one of the people
who are perfectly happy saying no.
Respect should be earned.
And without being
earned, you don't get it.
Right.
It's really that simple and not
everybody agrees and that's fine too.
Right.
There are people I refuse to work with.
It's it cuts both ways
and I realized that.
Okay, thank you.
Thanks.