我很高兴借这次机会，Mark Shuttleworth 到中国来的机会，为大家做一个现场演讲
Mark Shuttleworth 是 Ubuntu 的创始人，可能大家已经听说过他的大名了
去年在北航我们曾经做过一次这样的演讲，当时现场反应也比较热烈
所以这回 Mark 来中国的时候我们就安排了这次是在上海
因为在北京已经做过了，这也是一次难得的机会
我就不多说了，下面有请 Mark Shuttleworth 为大家讲述他自己的经历和有关开源软件的一些概念和故事，谢谢
Good afternoon everybody. It's wonderful to be here
Amy tells me that you would all be students of a whole bunch of different things
and I'm keen to know a little bit about you before I start at speaking
so could you give me some indication of what you guys are studying
How many guys here are studying business
here at university
Engineer?
Computer engineering
majority of you are studying computer engineering
How many of you will prefer to start your own businesses
and how many would prefer to start working in large company?
So how many would prefer to start working in a large company
and how many of you want to start your own businesses
I can tell you who's gonna be really wealthy out of the crowd
the people who put up their hands up to say they're gonna start their own businesses
What I thought I would talk about today is entrepreneurship because
I believe that economical change is just as important as technological change which is just as important as social change
And it's entrepreneurs who really drive economical change
It's entrepreneurs who effectively take new ideas, turn them into new businesses, and turn them into global phenomenons
And I'm convinced that this is a country which gonna produce
Many of the next generation of great entrepreneurs
So I feel that that would be an interesting thing to talk about
If I ask you to list some great businesses that have been started in the last
In the last 10 years. What companies, what names would you throw out
Who wants to suggest?
It's a great choice. Google is a great business started in the last 10 years.
Apple. Apple is a great business.
They've radically changed in the last 10 years. They've radically changed the way people think about Apple
10 years ago maybe everybody thought Apple was dying and today they're the darling
They're setting the trend. It was a very interesting example
What are the other companies you admire?
(inaudible) Another great company. But it's not a new company it's not really changing things
Other brands, tell me about the company you admire
NetApp. I don't know that
NetApp. OK That's very interesting
The fact that the businesses that are kinda defining our age are companies like ebay and Google
What's the Chinese equivalent of ebay?
Advantage of completely new technologies that didn't really exist 10 years ago.
They are all companies that effectively
We all have them as brand names today and we accept them today as great companies. But 10 years ago you couldn't even dream that a company like that could exist.
If you look at the wealth that's been created in technology over the last 10 years
It's largely being created using technology that just didn't exist in 1995
and built around communities and customer bases just didn't exist in 1995
That highlights what I think perhaps is the most important characteristics of great entrepreneurs
is that they understand change. They understand how the world is changing
And they very much want to be part of that change
I think if you as an entrepreneur if you want to be a great entrepreneur
Then you have to understand
How the world is changing, you have to understand how
Changes that are going on in the world are going to affect your country
This is a country of great change. If you look back 10 years, how would you say things have changed here?
What would you say are the key element of change that's going on today? The Internet
You feel very connected to the outside world, you feel like you can follow the news that you can follow technology developments firmly?
I think you can. I think you can sit here in university and you can know exactly what's going on in chemistry
you can exactly what's going on in physics, you can learn exactly what's going on in computer science, in business
That's amazing. We're the first generation to be able to do that
Our parents' generation, it took a very long time before an idea from one part of the world reached somewhere else in the world.
So this is the biggest change. I would predict, that over the next generation, china is going to be
The world in which you do business is going to become exactly like Africa
Exactly like Europe exactly like America in the sense that you will be able to to to to to participate
as first class citizens instantly in whatever busines sit is that you choose to participate in.
Okay
So what are the characteristics of great entrepreneurs? Does anybody want to suggest, what does it take to be a great entrepreneur?
Passion. I would say that's the number one characteristic. If you want to create well, if you want to build something
you are going to have to devote yourself to it, you have to devote yourself to it completely.
And that's actually quite difficult. Different distractions. It is easy to get a job that pays you good salaries.
It's easy to to live an average life today. But if you want to live an exceptional life, you have to be totally totally committed to an idea.
And it's much easier to be committed to that idea, if you actually really fascinated by it.
So the number one thing I will tell you is, if you want to create wealth, right, if you want to become very wealthy, if you want to be.
Like the founders of Google, or the founder of ebay or the founder of NetApp, or the founder of SalesForce.com.
You're going to have an idea that you find so fascinating that you're willing to devote yourself to i,t to the exclusion of all of the other easy opportunities.
that you face, right? I meet a lot of entrepreneurs, people who make billions and billions and billions of dollars.
And I don't know any one of them who's not totally passionate about what they do
and if you, um.
If you allow yourself effectively to be drawn in to the average flow, if you allow yourself to be,
to define your objectives in terms of what the large company is telling you to do
then it's hard to be so passionate about it, whereas if you say you are going to go out and drive that change
Then it's much easier to be really really passionate about.
What else can you say of entrepreneurs?
Innovation. Exactly. Innovation is all about change.
There are two ways to be successful
Two ways to be successful, and I suppose the most successful people have a bit of both of this, but one way to be successful is to be extremely efficient.
Right to take what you've been asked to do and to do it very, very efficiently.
Or if you're running a business to make sure that that business is very, very efficient, right? So say you're running an airline.
But one way you can succeed at this airline is making sure that you run a more efficient airline than all of your other competitors, right?
So that's a little bit like, do you have Avis in this country? The rental car company, Avis?
OK internationally there's a company called Avis, and its slogan is, we try harder.
Basically, what they're saying is, we do exactly the same thing as everybody else. We don't do anything differently, but we try harder, right?
Now most of the entrepreneurs that I meet, they don't fall into that category. They're not necessarily extremely efficient managers, they're not necessarily extremely.
Operationly strong, but what they do is they innovate. They change things.
Possibly the greatest lesson, I think that I've learned over the years is that most of the changes that are happening are changes that are happening in society, despite what you do.
Because it's such a huge global economy.
While you can change things and you can innovate, usually what's happening is that there is an underlying change going on in society.
So if you understand that underlying change and you understand how the position is so forward.
Then you can effectively ride the wave of that change very efficiently.
To to build a new kind of business. So while people sometimes say that, you know, the entrepreneur is the innovator.
Usually what's happening is the entrepreneur is just understanding change that's going on in society.
So if you understand how the Internet works, for example, before everybody else does, then you can predict.
That that will create demand for new kinds of services. And you can position yourself.
To offer those services before everybody else does, so it's not as though you're actually creating the Internet.
That's too big for any one person or one company to do
But if you understand how the Internet is going to change your society and the business world around you, then you can position yourself to be the more efficient operator.
For me, that's a lot more fun, right, to ride these waves of change and through society.
So the big waves of change that we've seen in my lifetime have been first starting in the early 80s, a wave of change towards globalization.
In 1980
If you had a million pounds in England, you weren't allowed to take that million pounds anywhere else to go and invest and create business.
It's almost crazy today, because Shanghai is a global capital, you have hundreds of billions of pounds coming through Shanghai every week, right?
But 27 years ago that didn't exist, that industry didn't exist because there were very strict rules about
Not investing outside of your own country. And in the last generation, basically all of those rules have have been swept away, so
some entrepreneurs made huge fortunes because they could see that globalization, or the forces of globalization, would mean that
Any particular kind of capacity anywhere in the world should
ltimately be priced the same way that if you could manufacture something in the UK for one price, to manufacture something in India for half that price, that all of that manufacturing capacity move.
So that's one huge change that went through society.
The second huge change that surfed through society in my lifetime was the Internet.
It's effectively meant that information could move at no cost instantly anywhere in the world, and at first it was capital that was able to move.
The next big change that scrape through society was information, making information effectively move very, very efficient.
And there are still blocks and barriers and firewalls and filtering and things like that, but the trend absolutely is to make sure that information is instantly available anywhere.
And people initially thought about that in terms of the ability to send stuff out.
But if you could set up a website, now you could reach every customer in the world, every technology can connect to customer in the world.
So the next big change.
That we're starting to see is kind of like that wave coming back at us.
So the first change is all about connecting the world so that companies who have a domain could send information out.
to provide services out to the edges of their network, right? But now what we are seeing is that the edges of the network are starting to talk back.
Basically, what's happening is that
information and content and ideas from the edges of the network were coming in and changing the center. So how many. Can you guys get access to Wikipedia?
Amazon's business success, the secret to Amazon's business success is their customers.
Is the people who come back to them and give them information. Amazon has the richest collection of information.
about books in the world, but they didn't build that knowledge. What they've done is they basically they started out
sending information out, they are providing a service globally. And then then the wave came back, and they started gathering back your knowledge, your ideas, your preferences,
your favorite books, your thoughts about a particular book, right? So you see how this change is happening.
The next generation of great businesses, I believe, are all going to reflect this.
Google reflects this. Google reflects this by taking every time you create a web page and you link to other web pages, you're telling Google what's important on the web.
Google is effectively using your knowledge from the edge of the network, right?
So maybe you (inaudible) connect all of those businesses and see that there is an underlying effect happening there, but there really is
Ebay. For example, ebay.
The value in ebay is not created by ebay, it's created by all of their uses. You go to ebay, people go to ebay because everybody else is going there.
You go to Wikipedia because everybody else is going there, you see, the values not being created at the center, and then exported. The values are being created at the edges and then brought back in.
I think, it's a very interesting example of how that phenomenon of the edges talking back to the center
Is changing the world of software. Right? It used to be that
the best way to build software was to hire very smart guys from all around the world and move them to the center.
So Microsoft and Oracle and SAP would go and hire people
and move them to Raymond or San Francisco or Germany, and they would have centralized development laboratories.
And then they would ship the results of that stuff back out to the edges of their network, right?
But today, free supper is turning that around and saying, OK,
let's find the smartest, most self motivated people who are interested in technology at the edges of an network. Let's harness and gather all of their thinking.
And bring it to the center. So we completely fundamentally change the way software is being produced.
And I think, just like Wikipedia is a better repository of knowledge than say an encyclopedia like world book.
or Encyclopedia Britannica, or I don't know what the equivalent Chinese is.
So it is that free software effectively is a better repository of technology expertise.
Then proprietary software, which is getting written at the center.
So it's interesting to me that free software actually started to happen before Wikipedia started to happen, before Amazon started to happen
before some of those other businesses, because with software, in the very early days of the Internet,
The people who participated in the Internet were mostly programmers, so they started to show this ability of harnessing knowledge from the edge of the network and moving into the center.
well before the industries did.
But I will predict to you that every single industry is going to be changed by this.
Think of the music industry today.
Today, the music industry still looks like that centralized kind of thing. Content is produced at the center and then shipped out.
To the edges, right? So what's going to be what's going to be like in ten years time or fifteen year's time is the opposite, content to be produced at the edges of the network and then shipped in.
You will define what the popular music is by talking to your friends, and in that conversation, out of that global conversation will come
the hits of the year. Rather than the hits of the year being defined at the center, and the moved out.
What are the industries? Engineers is very interesting at the moment, people understand the free software movement.
But I think we are going to see equivalent phenomenons happening in every category of engineering.
Motor cars, it doesn't make sense to have motor cars design same (inaudible)
And for each company to have to reinvent the wheel, it makes much more sense for us effectively, to evolve designs based on the best talent wherever it happens to be.
Over time, houses is now, there's now a website that's being set up, which effectively allows architects
to design houses using the same processes by which Wikipedia is written.
Using the same processes by which free software, by which Linux is written, the same processes by which Amazon gathers its databases.
Harnessing architectural talent from all around the world and producing a shared repository of architectural designs.
It's very hard for me to think of a single industry which is not going to be touched like this.
So as an entrepreneur, whatever your personal passions are, right, if you're interested in,
whatever you're interested in, start thinking about
how this process could affect your industry? if you're interested in chemistry. For example, someone who was asking me questions earlier and he's a chemist
Stop thinking about this. How could you aggregate
chemical knowledge from the edges of the network and build a shared repository like Wikipedia. And then how could you build a business around that.
How do you change the business model to reflect the changed operational model Because each of these, each of these changes.
Is powered by a technology change, but ultimately it's also an economic change.
And so so the business model of Google is very different to the business model of Microsoft.
Completely different, and Microsoft really needs to understand how they can evolve so that they keep up with the underlying changes.
So I also want to talk a little bit about free software as a platform for
for entrepreneurs, right? If you're an entrepreneur, your job is to close a gap.
To close an economic gap, to find an opportunity, and then build the infrastructure to service them the opportunity
If I look at all of the great technology businesses from NetApp, through, how many of the guys have used VMware?
so if you used VMWare, through
the big information service businesses like Google, Yahoo.
big electronic trading businesses like Schwab and ebay or something, all of these businesses were actually built out using free software components.
The value of the software industry is not the licensing cost of the software.
It's the value of the economic processes that you're able to set up using that software.
And if you're an entrepreneur, a technology entrepreneur today, it's worth thinking about the fact that you can get started faster, using free software.
You can customize the tools to your to your purposes faster, using free software.
You can effectively build your business much more efficiently using free software.
So I'm going to predict effectively that the best technology businesses over the next 15 or 20 years
are all going to be powered by free software, you too, and you guys get Youtube there? You can't? OK
Youtube is all built on free software. They use MySQL as a database, they use the Linux as the core operating system.
Their offering is proprietary in the sense that they don't give you their code, but all of the pieces that they need to build that business
are built on free software.
Over the next ten years is going to be consumer electronics. How many of you guys know about the one laptop per child project?
The thing about that is that there is functional computers at a very low price.
It was a complete inversion of the of the traditional way of looking at the PC market, the traditional way of looking at the PC market was
You set high price points like $700, $900, $1100, and then you try and squeeze as much as functionality
into those price points as you can.
But with the one laptop per child project, they turned it around, and they said,
This is actually here, let's define a useful amount of computational functionality that we can give here.
Let's see how cheaply we can produce that useful function.
This year, we can do it for $170 next year, we can do it for $130, year after that, we can do it for $99. And then we've got
$100 laptop, one laptop per child, and so my sense is that we're entering a time when
computing is going to be absolutely ubiquitously available. Your phone is basically a computer.
And Motorola says that 60% of their phones, within three years, are all going to run on Linux.
We don't yet know what people will do with those computing platforms.
So I think that a lot of the innovation, a lot of the economic, the next generation of big businesses are effectively going to be
handheld devices or powered by handheld devices, rather than being powered by incidents
or powered by the PC, because you have many, many more people who carry hand held devices than you do
have people sitting in front of a computer all the time. I've got a laptop sitting in the car right now, but I've got a phone with me right here.
So if you can provide services, if you can build new economic models around delivering services to people
with some sort of consumer electronic device, then you have a much bigger, effective, addressable model.
All the service that we saw first being generated around the Internet bank, amazon and ebay, etc, etc. Those are all going to move towards being focused to
targeted to consumer electronics. Small handheld device
And there will be great businesses built around those, and I hope that some of you will be will be building those businesses.
A little bit about Ubuntu. How many of you guys are familiar with Ubuntu?
About a third or a half.
Decisions is take some of these big changes to their natural conclusion. If you look at the licensing costs of operating system
It's been dropping and dropping and dropping, so we say, OK, what's the natural conclusion? The natural conclusion is that the business model completely changes.
And people just get rid of licensing all together, so that's why we make Ubuntu absolutely free available.
If you look at the amount of free software that's being used that is increasing steadily, like Apple now.
The Apple operating system consists of about 80% of it.
Is free software, and only about 20% of it is proprietary. So we say, fine, let's take that train.
Take that train to its natural conclusion. So all of Ubuntu is made up of free software.
Let's make sure that we build something which represents the natural conclusion.
Of that big thing.
Because the technology of that big change, then you become the platform.
So that's why I think of what you are so popular, because it best represents a fundamental shift that's going on in the software industry.
That these are the values that people are looking for. These are the things which empower people most efficiently.
And so as an entrepreneur, if you go into entrepreneurship, I wouldn't encourage you to do the same thing, right? Ask yourself the question.
What are the big changes that I'm interested in How will those affect the field that I'm interested in.
And how do I build something which best reflects that change, which best implements that change?